Guide to the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. records M0750
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. records
Bulk, 1966-1990
1966-2000
M0750
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
406.0 Linear feet (167 manuscript boxes; 214 cartons; 7 half-boxes)
The records of the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. (CRLA) contain administrative files, litigation files, and special program and subject files, dating from the founding of the organization in 1966 through circa 2000. Materials in the collection document CRLA's ongoing work to provide legal aid to farmworkers and the rural poor in California.
California Rural Legal Assistance Foundation
California Rural Legal Assistance Incorporated.
Restrictions
A small amount of material with privacy and confidentiality issues has been closed for 75 years from the date the material was created. Within this guide, this material will be marked with a Restricted Material note at the file level, specifying the extent of the closure period.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
The records of the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. (CRLA) contain administrative files, litigation files, and special program and subject files, dating from the founding of the organization in 1966 through circa 2000. Material in the collection documents CRLA's ongoing work to provide legal aid to farmworkers and the rural poor in California and highlights particular priority areas where advocacy efforts were focused, including employment, education, immigration, health and environmental safety. Also included in the collection are numerous files related to CRLA's development and survival as an organization. The history of its funding and re-funding by the Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and the Legal Services Corporation (LSC) is particularly well documented. The majority of material within the collection originated from CRLA's central administrative office in San Francisco, although some records from regional branch offices are present as well.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. to Stanford University, Special Collections in 1995, 2005, 2011, and 2013 (accessions 1995-085, 2005-077, 2011-059, 2011-160, and 2013-009). Materials from accessions 1995-085, 2005-077, 2011-059, and 2011-160 were processed between March 2011 and February 2013 and are listed in this finding aid.
Arrangement and Description
The collection is organized into nine record groups:
Record Group 1. Board of Directors
Record Group 2. Directors
Record Group 3. Administrative and Financial Files
Record Group 4. Communication and Development Files
Record Group 5. Advocacy
Record Group 6. Program Files
Record Group 7. Audiovisual Material
Record Group 8. Government Relations
Record Group 9. Born-Digital Material
Materials within an individual record group, or within a series or subseries of an individual record group, have been arranged alphabetically by box title. Box titles and subtitles may include a general description (i.e. financial files), a format term (i.e. pleadings) a subject term (i.e. mechanization), or the name of a specific legal case or individual person. Legal cases are alphabetized by the name of the primary plaintiff or defendant. As a second level of arrangement, some boxes have been organized chronologically (i.e. meeting files and similar types of material have been arranged chronologically when possible and relevant).
The majority of the collection has been described at the box level. Descriptions are meant to give researchers an overall sense of what will be found in the entire box but are not exhaustive and do not list the contents of every folder.
Historical Note
Founded in 1966 through a grant from the Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO), California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. (CRLA) was the first federally-funded rural legal services program as well as the first such statewide program. CRLA provides legal services to farmworkers, particularly migrant farmworkers, and the rural poor in California. James D. Lorenz Jr. was the founding director of CRLA and organizers César Chávez, Dolores Huerta and Larry Itliong were all members of its founding Board. There have now been five other directors: Cruz Reynoso, Martin R. Glick, Richard Baca, Alberto Saldamando, and the current director, José R. Padilla, whose tenure began in 1984.
As one of the original "War on Poverty" programs, CRLA was nationally renowned for pursuing high-impact class actions that benefitted millions of low-income people in California and nationally until the 1996 "Gingrich Congress" prohibited federally-funded legal services from participating in class-action litigation. Today, CRLA continues to assist individual clients and communities through alternative forms of litigation, remaining steadfastly committed to advocating for the rural poor as a class in order to address the root causes of poverty. To achieve this goal, CRLA has developed an effective organizational structure, with a central administrative office in San Francisco as well as numerous regional branch offices located near rural communities within California. Regional offices allow CRLA to make its services available to clients where they live, while the central office is able to direct priorities for the organization as a whole.
CRLA has traditionally focused its advocacy efforts around a set of strategic priority areas, including employment, housing, education, immigration, civil rights, health, and environmental safety. The organization has achieved legal success in all these areas. For example, an early CRLA advocacy effort led by Ralph S. Abascal—who joined CRLA as a staff attorney in 1968 and later became CRLA General Counsel for over twenty years—resulted in the eventual banning of DDT and other pesticides in the early 1970s. Other examples of successful litigation include Carmona v. Division of Industrial Safety (1975), a case that CRLA argued in the California Supreme Court and that led to the banning of EI Corito, the crippling short-handled hoe.
Other notable CRLA cases include Diana v. Board of Education (1970), in which CRLA challenged the practice of placing non-native English speakers into classes for the mentally disabled. CRLA was also instrumental in the passing of the Chacon-Moscone Bilingual-Bicultural Act of 1976, and enhanced the power of this Act in the case of Comite De Padres de Familia v. Riles (1985), which further defined the state's responsibility for supervising bilingual education programs. CRLA also achieved a victory for undocumented immigrants by securing the addition of the Special Agricultural Worker provision to the Immigration Reform and Control Act (IRCA). The provision allowed a million undocumented workers to become legalized. CRLA went on to litigate two of three "late amnesty cases" filed in the federal courts in California against the Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) for its misadministration of IRCA: Catholic Social Services (CCS) v. Meese (1986) and Zambrano v. INS (1988). During litigation that spanned over twenty years, the CCS case was argued at all levels of the federal courts including before the U.S. Supreme Court.
CRLA's priorities are revisited at least once every five years in the form of Statewide Priorities Conferences, and are also addressed through the formation of specific task forces aimed at identifying, understanding, and raising awareness about issues affecting the organization’s rural clients. Additional changes CRLA has undergone include the establishment of a Migrant Unit, in order to more effectively address issues faced by migrant farmworkers. Over the years, CRLA has worked hard to remain independent and true to its original mission, which has included collaboration with other legal services groups, such as the Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund (MALDEF), through activities such as co-counseling and the joint filing of amici briefs.
Despite being consistently praised by its clients and recognized by organizations such as the American Bar Association for providing high-quality legal services CRLA has been particularly subject to politically motivated efforts to defund the organization and has been forced to struggle for its survival. The 1970 veto by then Governor Ronald Reagan of CRLA's federal, OEO funding is perhaps the most notable example of this type of attack.
CRLA's relations with Reagan had been tense ever since CRLA litigation successfully blocked his attempts to cut California's welfare programs in 1967. Following these defeats in court, Reagan appointed Lewis K. Uhler, a former member of the John Birch Society as director of the State's OEO, an appointment that seemed clearly aimed at undermining CRLA. Uhler compiled and submitted to Reagan a report that listed 127 alleged incidents of CRLA misconduct, ranging from misuse of OEO funds to intentionally inciting prison riots. The report failed to acknowledge any of CRLA's significant accomplishments. On December 26, 1970, Regan vetoed the OEO $1.8 million grant for CRLA's 1971 refunding.
Although Reagan's veto was no surprise, the outrageous and libelous allegations contained in the Uhler Report prompted CRLA and its supporters to launch an ambitious campaign to save the organization. CRLA demanded an investigation into the Uhler charges and submitted its own report that refuted each incident cited in the Report. The Nixon administration appointed a commission consisting of the Chief Justices of three state Supreme Courts (all of them Republicans) to investigate. This commission conducted hearings throughout California (in which Uhler himself refused to appear or participate) and ultimately concluded that all the charges against CRLA were false.
The Uhler Report controversy was not only a formative moment in CRLA's history but by exposing the vulnerability of legal services to political attacks, led to the bi-partisan creation of the federal Legal Services Corporation (LSC) with the goal of reducing state and local interference under the OEO funding scheme. This controversy and its implications have been examined in numerous articles and studies, including the 1973 article published in The Hastings Law Journal by legal scholars Jerome B. Falk and Stuart R. Pollak, Political Interference with Publicly Funded Lawyers: The CRLA Controversy and The Future of Legal Services. The controversy is also treated in Michael Bennett and Cruz Reynoso's 1972 article in the UCLA Chicano-Latino Law Review, California Rural Legal Assistance (CRLA): Survival of a Poverty Law Practice.
Reagan's gubernatorial experience with CRLA led him throughout his subsequent Presidency to consistently seek the elimination of LSC and all federally-funded legal services. His efforts were continually blocked in Congress. Notwithstanding his inability to eliminate LSC, Reagan used his presidential power to appoint LSC members dedicated to eliminating the programs through politically-motivated investigations that interfered with program operations and often resulted in decreased funding. A continuing, decades-long series of audits, investigations and extraordinary conditions imposed on funding by LSC and/or its Office of Inspector General, have consumed thousands of hours of CRLA staff time and pro-bono efforts from supporting members of the Bar. In 1981, to help offset program cuts due to decreases in funding, CRLA and its supporters created the CRLA Foundation (CRLAF). The Foundation receives no federal funding, and is therefore able to undertake significant work that CRLA cannot because of federal restrictions on LSC-funded organizations.
Despite the many challenges CRLA has faced, the organization has shown a remarkable resilience throughout its nearly fifty years of operation. CRLA continues its unique mission, providing legal representation and other assistance to farmworkers and the rural poor in California, and has evolved into one of the most effective advocacy programs in the United States.
Abascal, Ralph S.; Baca, Richard; Chavez, Cesar, 1927-1993; Glick, Martin R.; Gonzales, Richard A., 1944-; Lorenz Junior, James D.; Miller, Tom; Padilla, José R.; Pearl, Richard M.; Rasmussen, Barbara; Reagan, Ronald; Reynoso, Cruz, 1931-; Rosenbaum, Stephen; Uhler, Lewis K.; White, Tony; Legal aid--California; Mexican Americans; Migrant agricultural laborers--California.
- Record Group 1. Board of Directors, circa 1966-1994
  Scope and Contents
  This record group contains agendas and minutes from the meetings of CRLA's Board of Directors/ Trustees. It also contains Board member training and orientation materials, committee and conference material, bylaws, rosters, and correspondence related to the Board’s activities. In addition to offering insight into the structural workings of CRLA as an organization, material in this record group provides a concise overview of CRLA's high-level concerns, priorities, and activities.
  - Series 1. Correspondence
    - Correspondence; includes letters and memos to/from State Bar of California, Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO); Directors James Lorenz, Cruz Reynoso, Marty Glick; law firms, legal aid organizations, Daniel Luevano, others; also reports and clippings included with correspondence (19 folders), 1966-1973 (Carton 15)
  - Series 2. Meeting and Conference Files
    - Advisory Committees; includes correspondence and meeting materials for regional office advisory committees (18 folders), 1986-1987 (Box 162)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (27 folders), 1966-1970 (Carton 31)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (5 folders), 1971 (Box 32)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (12 folders), 1971 (Box 38)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (21 folders), 1972-1973 (Carton 37)
    - Meetings; includes minutes; also sample packet for new Board members (6 folders), 1972-1973 (Box 16)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (15 folders), 1974-1976 (Carton 85)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (6 folders), 1976-1977, 1980 (Box 86)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (16 folders), 1976-1980 (Carton 84)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, memos, reports, supporting materials (12 folders), 1978, 1980-1981 (Carton 239)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, memos, reports, supporting materials (9 folders), 1982-1983 (Box 21)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (12 folders), 1983-1985 (Box 160)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, memos, reports, supporting materials (11 folders), 1985-1986 (Box 22)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, reports, memos, supporting materials (7 folders), 1980, 1987-1988 (Box 93)
    - Meetings; includes agendas, minutes, memos, reports, supporting materials (20 folders), 1988-1994 (Carton 20)
    - Meeting minutes (8 folders), 1972-1973, 1976-1979 (Box 83)
    - Meeting minutes (9 folders), circa 1972-1986 (Box 11)
    - Meeting minutes and related files (16 folders), 1973-1982 (Carton 176)
    - Priorities Conference materials; includes Board training material (4 folders), circa 1969-1985 (Box 377)
  - Series 3. Mixed Material
    - Mixed material; includes Board meeting attendance sign-in sheet; travel and training information; miscellaneous, loose materials related to funding, costs, administration, program update sheets (11 folders), circa 1988-1990 (Box 12)
    - Mixed material; includes meeting agendas, minutes, reports, clippings; also information on Board members (27 folders), circa 1982-1987 (Carton 35)
    - Mixed material; includes correspondence, bylaws, and rosters (14 folders), 1979-1986 (Carton 97)
    - Mixed material; includes orientation packets, responsibility and structure information, nominations, resolutions, and related material (24 folders), circa 1977-1983 (Carton 161)
    - Mixed material; includes bylaws, committees, memos, correspondence, and other materials (10 folders), 1971, 1974, 1979, 1985 (Box 260)
    - Mixed material; includes LSC news clippings, board clippings, and board rosters (6 folders), 1982-83, 1987, 1989 (Box 261)
- Record Group 2. Directors, circa 1966-1996
  This record group contains administrative and subject files related to the work of CRLA's Executive Directors, General Counsel ( Ralph S. Abascal), and Litigation Directors.
  - Series 1. Executive Directors, 1966-1990
    This series contains papers belonging to CRLA's six Executive Directors and includes correspondence, memos, meeting and committee material, subject files, and administrative records. Collection material related to the work of the directors can be found throughout the collection, as the scope of their activities touches upon all areas of the organization’s operations. The files in this series, however, were specifically labeled as belonging to one of the directors by CRLA staff and have therefore been arranged separately.
    The series has been divided into a subseries for each director:
    Subseries 1. James D. Lorenz, Jr., 1966-1969
    Subseries 2. Cruz Reynoso, 1969-1972
    Subseries 3. Martin R. Glick, 1972-1974
    Subseries 4. Richard Baca 1974-1976
    Subseries 5. Alberto Saldamando, 1976-1984
    Subseries 6. José R. Padilla, 1984-
    Note: Date ranges of these subseries reflect the period of each director’s tenure, although the subseries may contain some records from an earlier or later date.
    - Subseries 1. James D. Lorenz, Jr., 1966-1969
      - Alphabetical files; includes correspondence, notes, and other material (27 folders), circa 1969 (Carton 99)
      - Alphabetical files; includes correspondence, notes, and other material (12 folders), circa 1969 (Box 100)
    - Subseries 2. Cruz Reynoso, 1969-1972
      - CRLA v. Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO); includes OEO reports, evaluations,; also pleadings, refunding hearings, CRLA’s answer to the Uhler Report, related materials (30 folders), circa 1968-1972 (Carton 1)
      - Unions, clippings (8 folders), circa 1966-1967 (Box 2)
      - Post-CRLA career; includes correspondence and other material, 1986, 1988 (Box 262, Folder 13)
    - Subseries 3. Martin R. Glick, 1972-1974
      - Martin Glick papers; includes material on refunding and the National Health Law Program., 1974 (Box 262, Folders 1-2)
    - Subseries 4. Richard Baca, 1974-1976
      - Richard Baca papers; includes memos and correspondence on various topics., 1974-1977 (Box 262, Folders 3-9)
    - Subseries 5. Alberto Saldamando, 1976-1984
      - Attorney and legal cost subject files; includes attorney salary scale; ULWC contract negotiations; Serrano v. Priest; legal cost studies; Private Bar involvement files, (10 folders), 1977-1983 (Box 166)
      - Correspondence; correspondents include members of other legal services programs, CRLA central and regional office staff; topics include the ULWC strike in 1978. (17 folders), 1977-1984 (Box 70)
      - Meeting packets: mostly Board of Directors meetings; also Directing Attorneys meetings, other committee meetings; includes minutes, agendas, related memos, reports, clippings, notes (19 folders), 1977-1980 (Carton 10)
      - Mixed administrative and subject files; includes Migrant Legal Action Program (MLAP) workplans and related materials, LSC funding materials; also staff, Directing Attorney, and litigation meeting materials (25 folders), circa 1977-1980 (Carton 49)
      - Mixed administrative files; includes CRLA office merger files; Cooperative Legal Services Center (CLSC) termination; budget and cost studies; LSC regulations (9 folders), 1977-1978 (Box 164)
      - Mixed administrative and subject files; includes Priorities Conference materials, budget files, miscellaneous project proposals, research files, and articles (28 folders), 1977-1980 (Carton 50)
      - Mixed administrative files; includes memos and correspondence on the CRLA deficit and other topics., 1978, 1981-1984 (Box 262, Folders 10-12)
      - Mixed materials; includes correspondence, notes, memos, grant files, the CRLA Foundation, retrenchment, the organization's structure, and task forces such as labor and education (31 folders), 1975, 1978, 1980-1984 (Carton 102)
      - Mixed materials; includes correspondence, memos, and other documents related to the housing, education, and labor task forces (6 folders), 1981-1985 (Box 104)
      - Mixed materials; includes miscellaneous papers and correspondence, memos, reports, and other material on the proposed "alien registry" (7 folders), 1981-1983 (Box 131)
      - Mixed materials; includes correspondence, meeting material and notes, litigation and subject files, financial reports, miscellaneous loose files (32 folders), 1976-1983 (Carton 193)
      - Mixed meeting files; includes Asilomar and priority conferences, litigation and Board meetings; migrant, advisory, and finance committees; also miscellaneous meeting material and related reports (17 folders), 1979-1980 (Carton 197)
      - Mixed meeting and subject files; includes Project Advisory Group (PAG) files, CRLA structure committee, task force, and other meeting materials; also Reclamation Act research (12 folders), 1977-1978 (Box 163)
      - Mixed subject and legal program files; includes research on police stops of undocumented immigrants; Senior Citizens Law Program (SCLP); also Seniors United v. LSC (8 folders), 1977-1978 (Box 165)
      - Subject files; includes migrant unit issues, case load statistics, other topics (13 folders), circa 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      - Subject files; includes minority support project, White House consultation with farmworkers (6 folders), circa 1980-1981 (Box 4)
      - Subject files; miscellaneous, loose files; includes memos, reports, clippings (17 folders), circa 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - Tom Miller papers; includes correspondence, memoranda, and other material related to Miller's work as deputy director of CRLA (4 folders), 1978-1979 (Box 263)
    - Subseries 6. José R. Padilla, 1984-
      - Mixed materials; administrative files, memos, reports, notes, clippings, outreach materials (28 folders), circa 1983-1986 (Carton 46)
      - Mixed materials; includes correpsondence, memos, and other material (4 folders), 1981-1985, 1990 (Box 103)
      - Mixed materials; includes correspondence, memos, reports, and other material (11 folders), 1985-1986 (Box 140)
      - Mixed materials; includes correspondence, memos, reports, and other material (17 folders), 1986-1987 (Carton 141)
  - Series 2. General Counsel - Ralph S. Abascal, 1970-1996
    Ralph S. Abascal served as General Counsel to CRLA for over twenty years. This series contains material that was specifically labeled as belonging to Abascal or related to his work. It includes correspondence, notes, and working files on topics such as immigration, pesticides, and mechanization, as well as pleadings from cases related to these topics. Also included are typescripts, news clippings, and other publications related to Abascal's work, and his files related to LSC refunding and CRLA survival issues.
    - Agricultural issues; includes correspondence, memos, reports, research, and other materials related to issues such as pesticide use, agricultural mechanization, and related matters (17 folders), circa 1970-1980 (Box 130)